<article xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
	xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
	xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude' type="report">
	<title>Tool Accessibility</title>
	<subtitle>
		Defining a standard way to test tools for accessibility
	</subtitle>
	<para></para>
	<sect1 id="tool-accessibility-intro">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			While there has been an emphasis in web accessibility for
			websites and the retrofitting of existing web content there
			hasn't been a consistent effort to test content creation
			tools for their creation of accessible content and how
			accessible the tools themselves are.
		</para>
		<para>
			This project seeks to address these issues by providing both
			a methodology and a selection of tools to test. It also
			seeks to create awareness regarding testing methodologies
			and how they can be applied to evaluating technology.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="problem-statement">
		<title>Problem Statement</title>
		<para>
			Each California State University campus uses it own set of
			tools to develop content for their online delivery. In the
			past it was ok to use an HTML editor such as Adobe
			DreamWeaver to create content. Now faculty want immediate
			results and don't care as much about the underlying
			technology that allows to create content but want the
			content to be created with minimal effort and maximum
			results.
		</para>
		<para>
			Students expectations have also evolved over the years.
			Where it was OK to just convert a Word Document to HTML now
			students want better quality on their instructional
			materials.
		</para>
		<para>
			There are several tools available to help faculty in
			developing content both for their LMS content as well as for
			their web-based content. A sample of the tools is listed
			below:
		</para>
		<informaltable xml:id="list-of-tools-aaccessibility" rules="all"
			frame="box">
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td>
						<emphasis role="strong">Name of Tool</emphasis>
					</td>
					<td>
						<emphasis role="strong">Website</emphasis>
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Softchalk</td>
					<td>http://www.softchalk.com</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Lectora</td>
					<td>http://www.trivantis.com</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>ReadyGo</td>
					<td>http://www.readygo.com</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Articulate</td>
					<td>http://www.articulate.com</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>ToolBox</td>
					<td>http://www.toolbox.com</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Smart Builder</td>
					<td>http://www.suddenlysmart.com</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Adobe Captivate</td>
					<td>http://www.adobe.com/products/captivate/</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Camtasia</td>
					<td>http://www.techsmith.com/camtasia.asp</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</informaltable>
		<para>
			I am not aware at this time whether any studies beyond the
			vendors' claims of compliance that confirm or refute the
			vendors claims. This project seeks to provide an initial
			knowledge base regarding content creation tools
			accessibility and as a springboard for Universities to
			select their tools knowing that they produce accessible
			content
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="accessibility-methodology">
		<title>Methodology</title>
		<para>
			To avoid upsetting the balance in individual campuses the
			team will conduct a survey to determine which, if any,
			authoring tools are being used by each. This will provide an
			initial list of tools to evaluate.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="results">
		<title>Results</title>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="conclusions">
		<title>Conclusions</title>
	</sect1>
</article>