<book xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
	xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
	xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
	<info>
		<title>Distance Learning and Future Technologies</title>
		<subtitle>Where we are and how we got there</subtitle>
		<author>
			<personname>
				<firstname>Carlos</firstname>
				<surname>Araya</surname>
			</personname>
			<!-- 
				<affiliation>
				<jobtitle>Information Technology Consultant</jobtitle>
				<orgname>California State University, Chico</orgname>
				<orgdiv>Academic Technologies</orgdiv>
				</affiliation>
			-->
		</author>
		<legalnotice>
			<para>(C) 2008 Carlos Araya</para>
			<para>
				The views and opinions expressed in the following pages
				are those of the author and do not necessarily represent
				those of the staff at CSU, Chico or the California State
				University System
			</para>
			<para>
				Where the author was aware of an existing copyright
				claim the name of the trademark has been capitalized. No
				infringement is intended by the use of the trademarked
				names.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
	</info>
	<preface id="book-intro">
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			What started as an inquiry regarding the adoption, use and
			support for Synchronous Distance Learning Programs evolved,
			to me, into an exploration of the people and the tools that
			we use to deliver Distance Learning, both Synchronous and
			Asynchronous and where the technology and people are going
			in this Brave New World.
		</para>
		<para>
			Even though I have been working on Distance Learning for 10
			years I had never really realized the breadth and depth
			necessary for online courses, training workshops to be
			delivered successfully. From accessibility expert who ensure
			that the content is usable by all students, to the
			instructional designers and trainers who make sure that
			faculty are up to speed with the tools they are going to
			use, to the system administrators who make sure that the
			system is reliable and doesn't crash when you least expect
			it.
		</para>
		<para>
			That's why I decided to go for breadth first and then, if
			possible, go for depth. There is too much to cover in order
			to really understand Distance Learning to really go much in
			depth about it. I hope that I have done justice to the
			material I have covered.
		</para>
		<para>Carlos</para>
		<sect1 id="book-thanks">
			<title>Acknowledgements</title>
			<para>
				Even though there is one name in this report there are
				several people who have helped tremendously in the
				development of the content and ideas on this survey
			</para>
			<para>
				The people who worked with me in DLT Classroom Support
				at CSU, Chico: Buzz, Stephen, Gene and the student
				assistant. You make it fun and challenging and
				intellectually stimulating to work in the support team.
			</para>
			<para>
				Edits and additional items were added to this report
				during the Collaboration 2008 Conference in Salt Lake
				City, Utah and CATS 2008 in Rhonert Park, California.
				Both conferences have been very intellectually
				stimulating environments with people who are brilliant
				at what they do.
			</para>
		</sect1>
	</preface>
	<part id="survey-related">
		<title>Survey Report and Related Documents</title>
		<partintro>
			<para>
				The survey described below was commissioned by CSU,
				Chico as an environmental scan for Distance Learning
				tools and support models. as indicated in the report
				introduction, CSU, Chico is starting to look at new
				technologies and methods to support Distance Learning
				programs.
			</para>
			<para>
				The purpose of the survey is not to interpret the data
				but to raises questions and issues for future research
				and discussion. We are too early in the research process
				to be able to draw any substantive conclusions at this
				point of the process. However it is useful to know what
				other schools are doing and have contact information to
				pursue further questions or for additional research.
			</para>
		</partintro>
		<chapter id="survey">
			<title>Survey Report</title>
			<sect1 id="intro">
				<title>Introduction and Rationale</title>
				<para>
					No one wants to work in a vacuum. CSU, Chico has
					used the same basic technology setup to deliver
					synchronous online instruction since 2000 when the
					satellite program was transitioned to an online
					format. In the mean time technology has progressed
					at an accelerated rate... where in 2000 there were a
					few vendors now there are several. Tools have been
					developed to both support and augment the
					synchronous tools used.
				</para>
				<para>
					The survey grew up of a need to evaluate what other
					schools are doing in terms of synchronous distance
					learning tools and how these tools are being
					supported by the campuses. Whatever the reasons for
					having skipped a technological generation are; now
					CSU, Chico needs to play catch up. The information
					gathered in this survey will inform later steps and
					stages in our new Distance Learning tools selection
					process, support models and procedures and,
					eventually, lead to a model that will take CSU,
					Chico to a leadership position in Distance Learning.
				</para>
				<sect2 id="survey-thanks">
					<title>Acknowledgements</title>
					<para>
						Even though there is one name in this report
						there are several people who have helped
						tremendously in the development of the content
						and ideas on this survey
					</para>
					<para>
						The people who work with me in DLT Classroom
						Support: Buzz, Stephen, Gene and the student
						assistant. You make it fun and challenging and
						intellectually stimulating to work in the
						support team.
					</para>
					<para>
						To the Wimba Support Team: Laura, Scott, Ann,
						Jan. Thanks for the feedback and for the
						intellectually stimulating conversations.
					</para>
					<para>
						Edits and additional items were added to this
						report during the Collaboration 2008 Conference
						in Salt Lake City, Utah. It has been a very
						intellectually stimulating environment with
						people who are brilliant at what they do
					</para>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>

			<sect1 id="methodology">
				<title>Methodology and Survey Development</title>
				<para>
					When developing the methodology it was decided that
					a survey was the best tool to conduct this project.
					Because surveys are static instruments it was also
					decided to request contact information for potential
					follow up questions. The survey will certainly
					generate more questions than the data can answer. It
					has been made clear from the beginning to
					participants that, while their personally
					identifying information would be kept confidential,
					the researcher will contact those institutions whose
					information has generated new research questions.
				</para>

				<para>
					The survey was broken into 4 distinct areas:
				</para>

				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Informed Consent as required by the
							University's Human Subject Review Committee
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Demographics about the respondent and their
							institution
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Demographics about the respondent
							institution's Synchronous and Asynchronous
							courses, LMS Integration and the way in
							which the software used for Distance
							Learning was selected
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Specific information about the respondent's
							Synchronous Distance Learning Software and
							its support model for both faculty and
							students
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>

				<para>
					Once the author had an initial version of the survey
					it was reviewed by several members of Academic
					Technologies and after several meetings the final
					version of the survey was completed and submitted to
					Human Subjects for review and approval. See
					<xref linkend="Lessons" />
					for some of the lessons learned in the development
					and administration of the survey instrument.
				</para>

				<para>
					When the survey instrument was developed then the
					team had to decide how to deliver the instrument.
					The author briefly considered creating a PDF and
					sending it via email to potential respondents
					allowing them to self-select for completion of the
					survey. This was deemed impractical due to the
					number of responses expected. The Center for
					Excellence in Teaching and Learning (CELT) owns a
					license for Survey Monkey (
					<link xlink:href="http://www.surveymonkey.com" />
					). Since the technology is available and it makes
					the collection of data more manageable it was
					decided to use Survey Monkey to administer the
					survey and collect the results.
				</para>

				<para>
					The survey was originally sent to 5 lists with 2
					additional groups (Community College Users and
					Community College Distance Learning Coordinators)
					being added later when the survey was forwarded to
					community college users and Distance Learning
					Coordinators. These additional groups of respondent
					explain the high percentage of respondents from
					Community Colleges.
				</para>

				<para>
					The survey was sent originally to the following
					lists:
				</para>

				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<link
								xlink:href="http://it.coe.uga.edu/itforum/">
								IT Forum:
							</link>
							A list for instructional designers and
							people who work developing instruction, both
							in education and corporate settings.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<link xlink:href="http://cats.cdl.edu/">
								Community of Academic Technology Staff:
							</link>
							A community for people who work in academic
							technologies, initially across the
							California State University System and now
							open for membership
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<link xlink:href="http://www.nmc.org/">
								New Media Center Technology Advisory
								Board (TAB):
							</link>
							Members-Only list for knowledge sharing
							among the members of the New Media Center
							Consortium
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<link
								xlink:href="http://www.educause.edu">
								Educause:
							</link>
							General Member list for Educause
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<link
								xlink:href="http://lcin.wordpress.com/">
								LCIN Steering Committee:
							</link>
							<acronym>LCIN</acronym>
							(Leading Campuses International Network) is
							a group of former WebCT Institute program
							members who have regrouped under the name
							LCIN for the purpose of "Advancing effective
							use of course technologies by connecting
							people with good ideas…" (taken from LCIN
							website)
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>

				<para>
					The variety of groups the survey was sent to was
					deliberate. The team wanted to ensure responses that
					were as varied as possible. As mentioned above, when
					the chance was offered to have the survey forwarded
					to Community College users it was deemed a good
					opportunity to expand the base of respondents and to
					gather information towards future research.
				</para>

				<sect2 id="future" xml:id="Lessons">
					<title>Lessons Learned</title>
					<para>
						No matter how careful you are in developing a
						survey there are always things that could have
						been done different to improve the survey's
						overall response rate.
					</para>
					<para>Some of the specific issues include:</para>

					<sect3 id="clarification">
						<title>
							Clarification about the voluntary nature of
							the survey
						</title>
						<para>
							For some of the respondents from the
							community colleges in particular there was a
							perception that they were required to
							complete the survey whether it applied to
							them or not. Some of the feedback seems to
							indicate that they were required to complete
							the survey regardless of what the informed
							consent statement indicates.
						</para>
						<para>
							This may have had to do with the fact that
							for this particular group the survey
							originated from the Community College's
							Chancellors office and not directly from the
							authors of the survey and therefore carried
							a more authoritative message to those who
							received it
						</para>
						<para>
							Future surveys should clearly indicate and
							request people who forward the survey
							indicate that participation in the survey is
							strictly voluntary.
						</para>
					</sect3>
					<sect3 id="clarity">
						<title>
							Survey Clarity and Specific Language in
							Instructions
						</title>
						<para>
							As clear as we thought we had made the
							survey there was still a lot of confusion as
							to who the target audience was and who
							should answer the survey. Some people passed
							it over to their Distance Learning
							coordinators and others completed the survey
							as best as they could.
						</para>
						<para>
							Even among the Community College's Distance
							Learning Coordinators there was confusion as
							to what information the survey sought to
							gather. There was an email where a Distance
							Learning Coordinator who indicated that the
							answers just provided were of no use as
							survey material because the coordinator had
							not realized that were were requesting
							information about synchronous Distance
							Learning and his program was fully
							asynchronous. While not a generalized
							comment it calls into question the clarity
							of the instructions provided with the
							survey.
						</para>
						<para>
							Our expectation when developing the survey
							was that people who received it but were not
							able to answer it would pass it along to
							whoever they thought would be able to
							complete it for their institution. This was
							not the case which probably accounts for the
							number of faculty who completed the survey.
							See
							<xref linkend="user-distribution" />
							for respondents' role within their
							institutions.
						</para>

					</sect3>

					<sect3 id="wording">
						<title>
							Question Wording and Stating Quantities
						</title>
						<para>
							In addition to the question about the
							clarity of the instructions there was some
							feedback regarding the wording of some of
							the questions, in particular those that
							requested distinction between synchronous
							and asynchronous Distance Learning courses.
						</para>
						<para>
							Where we ask number of courses that are
							synchronous and asynchronous Distance
							Learning courses it may have been better to
							use percentages rather than number of
							courses to eliminate part of the confusion
							created by the wording of the questions.
						</para>
						<para>
							We also assumed a level of understanding
							from our audience in terms of what the
							objectives of the survey were. There was a
							lot of confusion and it was clear in
							comments and direct feedback that this was
							not always the case
						</para>
					</sect3>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>

			<sect1 id="analysis">
				<title>Analysis</title>
				<para>
					The following pages present a question by question
					analysis of the survey, along with preliminary
					observations and comments about each individual
					question, along with responses marked as "other"
					that are interesting and that may merit additional
					research or analysis.
				</para>

				<para>
					<emphasis role="strong">
						There was a total of 250 responses with a 52%
						completion rate of 130 complete responses.
					</emphasis>
				</para>
				<sect2 id="respondents-institution">
					<title>Respondent's institution</title>
					<table xml:id="question1" rules="all" frame="box">
						<caption>Respondent's Institution</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									1. Which best defines your
									institution?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Community College</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>State College/University</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Research University</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Trade School</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Online University</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 1 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 1 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q1graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>

					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						1:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q1" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>
									<emphasis role="strong" />
								</td>
								<td>
									<emphasis role="strong">
										Responses
									</emphasis>
								</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Community College</td>
								<td>100</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>State College/University</td>
								<td>60</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Research University</td>
								<td>44</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Trade School</td>
								<td>3</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Online University</td>
								<td>3</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
								<td>28</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>

				</sect2>

				<sect2 id="respondents-" xml:id="user-distribution">
					<title>Respondent's within institution</title>
					<table xml:id="question2" rules="all" frame="box">
						<caption>
							Defining User's Role within their
							institution
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									2. Which best defines your at your
									institution?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Administrator</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Director</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Manager</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Supervisor</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Technology Staff</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Faculty</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 2 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 2 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q2graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>

					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						2:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q2" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>
									<emphasis role="strong" />
								</td>
								<td>
									<emphasis role="strong">
										Responses
									</emphasis>
								</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Administrator</td>
								<td>35</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Director</td>
								<td>43</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Manager</td>
								<td>17</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Supervisor</td>
								<td>8</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Technology Staff</td>
								<td>33</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Faculty</td>
								<td>68</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
								<td>34</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>

				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="contact-request">
					<title>Contact request</title>
					<table xml:id="question3" rules="all" frame="box">
						<caption>Contact request</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									3. Is it OK if we contact you with
									additional questions?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Yes</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>No</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 3 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 3 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q3graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>

					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						3:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q3" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Responser</td>
								<td>Yes</td>
								<td>No</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Responses</td>
								<td>162</td>
								<td>88</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>

				<sect2 id="contact-info">
					<title>Contact Information</title>
					<table xml:id="question4" rules="all" frame="box">
						<caption>Contact Information</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									4. If you answered "yes" to the
									question above, please complete the
									information below.
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Respondent's Name</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Institution Name</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Email</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Phone</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para>
						The responses for this question are confidential
						information and therefore not shared as part of
						this report.
					</para>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="total-ftes">
					<title>Total FTEs for current term</title>
					<table xml:id="question5" rules="all" frame="box">
						<caption>Current FTEs for current term</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									5. What is your FTE for all classes
									offered in the current term?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>1 - 1000</td>
								<td>15000 - 20000</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1000 - 5000</td>
								<td>20000 - 30000</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>5000 - 10000</td>
								<td>30000 - 50000</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>10000 - 15000</td>
								<td>50000 or more</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 5 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 5 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q5graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>

					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						5:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q5" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Total FTEs</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1 - 1000</td>
								<td>34</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1000 - 5000</td>
								<td>18</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>5000 - 10000</td>
								<td>29</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>10000 - 15000</td>
								<td>20</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>15000 - 20000</td>
								<td>17</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>20000 - 30000</td>
								<td>10</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>30000 - 50000</td>
								<td>6</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>50000 or more</td>
								<td>3</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="students-enrolled-in-dl">
					<title>
						Students Enrolled in Distance Learning program
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question6" rules="all" frame="box">
						<caption>
							Students Enrolled In Distance Learning
							program
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									6. How many students are enrolled in
									your distance learning program?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>1 - 100</td>
								<td>2000 - 5000</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>101 - 500</td>
								<td>5000 - 10000</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>501 - 1000</td>
								<td>10001 or more</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1001 - 2000</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 6 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 6 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q6graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>

					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						6:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q6" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Students Enrolled</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1 - 100</td>
								<td>23</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>101 - 500</td>
								<td>25</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>501 - 1000</td>
								<td>15</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1001 - 2000</td>
								<td>16</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>2000 - 5000</td>
								<td>33</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>5000 - 10000</td>
								<td>15</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>10001 or more</td>
								<td>10</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="system-used-to-deliver">
					<title>
						Systems used to deliver synchronous Distance
						Learning
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question7" rules="all" frame="box">
						<caption>
							Systems used to deliver synchronous Distance
							Learning
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									7. What system(s) do you use for
									delivering synchronous distance
									learning instruction? (Select all
									that apply.)
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>
									Acrobat Connect Professional
									<sbr />
									(formerly Macromedia Breeze)
								</td>
								<td>Wimba Live Classroom</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Elluminate Live</td>
								<td>Centra</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Webex</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 7 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 7 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q7graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>

					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						7:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q7" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Software Used</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>
									Acrobat Connect Professional
									<sbr />
									(formerly Macromedia Breeze)
								</td>
								<td>25</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Elluminate Live</td>
								<td>40</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>WebEx</td>
								<td>5</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Wimba Live Classroom</td>
								<td>19</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Centra</td>
								<td>2</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other</td>
								<td>74</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
					<para>
						The variety of answers grouped under the "other"
						category prohibits listing them all therefore
						some salient points will be discussed.
					</para>

					<blockquote>
						<para>
							Custom Flash Media Server applications
						</para>
					</blockquote>

					<para>
						Either as a standalone application or as part of
						Accrobat connect Professional, flash is a very
						flexible delivery platform. In addition to the
						modules or "pods" there is the flexibility of
						building local "pods" to acomodate local needs
						and locally required elements.
					</para>

					<blockquote>
						<para>
							WebCT, some Windows Media streaming,
							correspondence, and telecourses
							(correspondence plus videotape). We DO NOT
							design courses for synhronous delivery. It
							prohibits participation by many students,
							and doesn't work well across time zones. We
							have students all over the world and that
							makes synchrnous media a no-go.
						</para>
					</blockquote>

					<para>
						World-wide access is becoming more and more of
						an issue. With online access not being
						geographically restricted neither are the
						options to take online courses. Schools like
						Chico have a set schedule where the students
						have the option of engaging with the content
						either live or via archived recordings of class
						sessions.
					</para>
					<para>
						Other schools have decided not to implement
						synchronous programs for a variety of reasons or
						have limited the use of synchronous tools to
						individual faculty members.
					</para>
					<blockquote>
						<para>
							We offer live videoconferences, not avail.
							on line
						</para>
						<para>Poly COM, Apple iChat, DVTS, Skype</para>
						<para>
							Even though you have only listed web
							conference tools as synchronous DL, we still
							use interactive, two-way video
						</para>
						<para>
							Mediasite by Sonic Foundry Video
							Conferencing (Tandberg h.323)
						</para>
						<para>
							Note: currently we do not use synchronous
							distance learning over the Internet. We do
							offer a suite of telecourses, a few
							featuring live lectures, most recorded.
							Increasingly these lectures are being
							integrated into our asynchronous online
							courses as streaming RealMedia. Our plans
							are to migrate to a Flash-based delivery....
						</para>
						<para>
							Although we offer distance learning via
							correspondence and Moodle, we do not offer
							any synchronous distance learning
							instruction
						</para>
						<para>
							Tandberg. polycom, and other
							telecommunications systems. Marratech
							netmeeting We use IP based Polycom codecs
							for two way communication
						</para>
					</blockquote>
					<para>
						A suprisingly large number of respondents,
						mostly from Community Colleges continue to use
						their video infrastructure for delivering
						instructional content. They also make extensive
						use of cable television channels and satellite
						television (Direct TV or Dish Network) for
						delivering instruction
					</para>

					<blockquote>
						<para>
							...The California Community Colleges
							Chancellor's Office provides Elluminate Live
							through CCCConfer.org and this can be used
							for chat and synchronous office hours but
							we're not using it now for course delivery.
						</para>
						<para>
							ReadyTalk (I am also staff at UCSD where I
							have a ReadyTalk account and prefer it over
							Elluminate, aka. CCCConfer)
						</para>

						<para>
							Really not doing much, if any, synchronous
							instruction, but CCC Confer offers
							Elluminate Live, which may be getting some
							minimal usage. However, the DE Committee and
							IT are planning to buy EL or other platform
							in the near future.
						</para>
					</blockquote>

					<para>
						CCCConfer (
						<link
							xlink:href="http://www.cccconfer.org/index1.aspx">
							http://www.cccconfer.org/index1.aspx
						</link>
						) provides Synchronous conferencing services for
						the 108 campuses of the California Community
						College system. The service initially used Wimba
						products but now has changed to Elluminate Live.
					</para>

					<para>
						There also seems to be a trend in asynchronous
						courses to use the synchronous tools built into
						the LMS (Moodle, Angel, Desire2Learn,
						Blackboard, eCollege, WebCT and Etudes NG were
						mentioned as delivery vehicles.) A concern with
						this model is the strength of the LMS network
						connection, the hardware it is running on and
						the number of simultaneous connections
					</para>
					<para>
						Etudes NG should be singled out and analyzed in
						more detail. Originally a project developed by
						an Instructor at Foothill College as an
						alternative to the big commercial Learning
						Management Systems; Etudes morphed into a Sakai
						derivative driven by a Consortium (
						<link
							xlink:href="http://www.etudesproject.org/">
							http://www.etudesproject.org/
						</link>
						) with a current membership of 23 community
						colleges.
					</para>


				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="how-long-using">
					<title>How long have you used the software</title>
					<table xml:id="question8" rules="all" frame="box">
						<caption>
							Students Enrolled In Distance Learning
							program
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									8. How long have you been using your
									synchronous distance learning
									delivery software?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Currently in pilot phase</td>
								<td>Between 2 and 3 years</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Less than 6 months</td>
								<td>Between 3 and 4 years</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Between 6 months and 1 year</td>
								<td>Between 4 and 5 years</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Between 1 and 2 years</td>
								<td>More than 5 years</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 8 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 8 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q8graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>

					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						8:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q8" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Length of Time</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Currently in Pilot Phase</td>
								<td>24</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Less than 6 months</td>
								<td>6</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Between 6 months and 1 year</td>
								<td>13</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Between 1 and 2 years</td>
								<td>17</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Between 2 and 3 years</td>
								<td>16</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Between 3 and 4 years</td>
								<td>11</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Between 4 and 5 years</td>
								<td>8</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>More than 5 years</td>
								<td>2</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="integrate-with-lms">
					<title>Do you integrate with your LMS</title>
					<table xml:id="question9" rules="all" frame="box">
						<caption>
							Do you integrate with your LMS?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									9. Do you integrate your synchronous
									distance learning software with your
									Learning Management System (LMS)?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Yes</td>
								<td>No</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 9 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 9 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q9graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>

					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						9:
					</para>
					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q9" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Do you integrate?</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Yes</td>
								<td>75</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>No</td>
								<td>62</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="what-system">
					<title>
						If you integrate, what system do you integrate
						with?
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question10" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							Which LMS do you integrate with
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									10. If you answered yes to question
									#9; which LMS do you use on campus?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>(Open Ended Answer)</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 10 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 10 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q10graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>

					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						10:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q10" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>What system</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Blackboard</td>
								<td>30</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>WebCT</td>
								<td>15</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Angel</td>
								<td>4</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Desire2Learn</td>
								<td>9</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Moodle</td>
								<td>8</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>eCollege</td>
								<td>5</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Etudes NG</td>
								<td>1</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="same-lms-as-oncampus">
					<title>
						Is it the same system used for on-campus
						classes?
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question11" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							Is it the same system used for on-campus
							classes?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									Is it the same system used for
									on-campus classes?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Yes</td>
								<td>No</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 11 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 11 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q11graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						11:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q11" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Same System</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Yes</td>
								<td>83</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>No</td>
								<td>10</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="selection-process">
					<title>
						Who selected the software you are currently
						using
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question12" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							Who selected your current distance learning
							software?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									12. Who from your institution
									selected your current distance
									learning software?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Administration</td>
								<td>
									Collaborative Group
									(Faculty/Administrators/Students)
								</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Faculty Committee</td>
								<td>Academic Technology Committee</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 12 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 12 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q12graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						12:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q12" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Who Selected</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Administration</td>
								<td>22</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Faculty Committee</td>
								<td>12</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>
									Collaborative Group
									<sbr />
									(Faculty/administrators/Students)
								</td>
								<td>48</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Academic Technology Committee</td>
								<td>31</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
								<td>24</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="distance-learning-classes-per-term">
					<title>
						How many classes are considered distance
						learning per term?
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question13" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							How many classes are considered distance
							learning per term?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									13. How many classes are considered
									distance learning per term?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>1 - 10</td>
								<td>300 - 500</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>11 - 100</td>
								<td>501 - 1000</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>101 - 200</td>
								<td>1001 or more</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 13 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 13 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q13graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						13:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q13" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Number of Classes</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1 - 10</td>
								<td>17</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>11 - 100</td>
								<td>51</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>101 - 200</td>
								<td>40</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>300 - 500</td>
								<td>17</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>501 - 1000</td>
								<td>10</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1000 or more</td>
								<td>2</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2
					id="synchronous-distance-learning-classes-per-term">
					<title>
						Synchronous Distance Learning classes per term
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question14" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							How many distance learning classes are
							considered synchronous?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									14. How many distance learning
									classes are considered synchronous?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>1 - 10</td>
								<td>300 - 500</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>11 - 100</td>
								<td>501 - 1000</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>101 - 200</td>
								<td>1001 or more</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 14 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 14 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q14graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						14:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q14" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Number of Classes</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1 - 10</td>
								<td>87</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>11 - 100</td>
								<td>37</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>101 - 200</td>
								<td>0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>300 - 500</td>
								<td>0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>501 - 1000</td>
								<td>3</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1000 or more</td>
								<td>0</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2
					id="asynchronous-distance-learning-classes-per-term">
					<title>
						Asynchronous Distance Learning classes per term
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question15" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							How many distance learning classes are
							considered asynchronous?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									15. How many distance learning
									classes are considered synchronous?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>1 - 10</td>
								<td>300 - 500</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>11 - 100</td>
								<td>501 - 1000</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>101 - 200</td>
								<td>1001 or more</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 15 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 15 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q15graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						15:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q15" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Number of Classes</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1 - 10</td>
								<td>33</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>11 - 100</td>
								<td>46</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>101 - 200</td>
								<td>0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>300 - 500</td>
								<td>0</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>501 - 1000</td>
								<td>12</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>1000 or more</td>
								<td>0</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2
					id="who-maintains-your-distance-learning software">
					<title>
						Who maintains your distance learning software?
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question16" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							16. Who maintains your distance learning
							software? (Select all that apply.)
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									16. Who maintains your distance
									learning software? (Select all that
									apply.)
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Faculty Development Center</td>
								<td>
									Dedicated distance learning support
									group
								</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Help Desk</td>
								<td>Third Party (ASP or Hosted)</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 16 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 16 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q16graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						16:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q16" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Who Maintains</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Faculty Development Center</td>
								<td>12</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Dedicated</td>
								<td>53</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>
									Third Party
									<sbr />
									(ASP or Hosted)
								</td>
								<td>35</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="faculty-technical-support">
					<title>
						How do faculty get technical support for
						distance learning software?
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question17" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							How do faculty get technical support for
							distance learning software?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									17. How do faculty get technical
									support for distance learning
									software? (Select all that apply.)
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Email</td>
								<td>In Person</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Telephone</td>
								<td>Synchronous Text Chat</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 17 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 17 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q17graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						17:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q17" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>
									How is technical
									<sbr />
									support provided
								</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Email</td>
								<td>114</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Telephone</td>
								<td>116</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>In Person</td>
								<td>107</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Synchronous Text Chat</td>
								<td>27</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
								<td>0</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2
					id="faculty-technical-support-same-as-oncampus">
					<title>
						Is this the same group that offers general
						technical support for faculty?
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question18" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							Is this the same group that offers general
							technical support for faculty?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									18. Is this the same group that
									offers general technical support for
									faculty?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Yes</td>
								<td>No</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 18 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 18 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q18graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						18:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q18" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>
									Is it the same as on-campus support
								</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Yes</td>
								<td>78</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>No</td>
								<td>51</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="faculty-pedagogical-support">
					<title>
						How do faculty get pedagogical support for
						distance learning?
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question19" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							How do faculty get pedagogical support for
							distance learning?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									19. How do faculty get pedagogical
									support for distance learning?
									(Select all that apply.)
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Email</td>
								<td>In Person</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Telephone</td>
								<td>Synchronous Text Chat</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 19 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 19 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q19graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						19:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q19" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>
									How is pedagogical
									<sbr />
									support provided
								</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Email</td>
								<td>89</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Telephone</td>
								<td>83</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>In Person</td>
								<td>108</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Synchronous Text Chat</td>
								<td>18</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
								<td>0</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2
					id="faculty-pedagogical-support-same-as-oncampus">
					<title>
						Is this the same group that offers general
						technical support for faculty?
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question20" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							Is this the same group that offers general
							technical support for faculty?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									19. How do faculty get pedagogical
									support for distance learning?
									(Select all that apply.)
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Yes</td>
								<td>No</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 20 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 20 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q20graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						18:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q20" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>
									Is it the same as on-campus support
								</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Yes</td>
								<td>75</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>No</td>
								<td>50</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="student-technical-support">
					<title>
						How do students get technical support for
						distance learning?
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question21" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							How do faculty get technical support for
							distance learning software?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									21. How do students get technical
									support for distance learning?
									(Select all that apply.)
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Telephone</td>
								<td>Chat</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Email</td>
								<td>In Person</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 21 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 21 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q21graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						21:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q21" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>
									How is student
									<sbr />
									support provided
								</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Email</td>
								<td>105</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Telephone</td>
								<td>111</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>In Person</td>
								<td>34</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Synchronous Text Chat</td>
								<td>71</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Other (please specify)</td>
								<td>35</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>
				</sect2>
				<sect2
					id="student-technical-support-same-as-oncampus">
					<title>
						Is it the same as general student technical
						support?
					</title>
					<table xml:id="question22" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<caption>
							Is it the same as general student technical
							support?
						</caption>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>
									22. Is it the same as general
									student technical support?
								</td>
								<td />
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>Yes</td>
								<td>No</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</table>
					<para />
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 22 of the
							Survey
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Graph Showing Results for Question 22 of the
							survey
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5in"
								height="4in" format="PNG" fileref="./images/q22graph.png" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para />
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						The the following were the responses to question
						22:
					</para>

					<informaltable xml:id="distribution-q22" rules="all"
						frame="box">
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>
									Is it the same as on-campus support
								</td>
								<td>Responses</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>Yes</td>
								<td>74</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>No</td>
								<td>53</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable>

					<blockquote>
						<para>
							None systemic - from the professor by e-mail
						</para>
					</blockquote>
					<para>
						A surprising number of instructors find
						themselves also having to fill the role of
						technical support for their students. This may
						be tied to "lone ranger" faculty who decided to
						implement synchronous solutions on their own.
					</para>
					<blockquote>
						<para>
							... website, take Intro to Online Learning
							course
						</para>
						<para>online tutorials and documentation</para>
						<para>
							online knowledge base and documentation
						</para>
					</blockquote>

					<para>
						Many responses include online resources as a
						means to support students taking online courses.
						It would be interesting to see what led to this
						kind of support and what the difference would be
						with a traditional physical help desk model
					</para>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>
		</chapter>
	</part>
	<part id="litreview">
		<title>Literature Review</title>
		<partintro>
			<para></para>
		</partintro>
		<chapter id="review">
			<title>
				Literature Review on Distance Learning and Related
				Technologies
			</title>
			<para></para>
		</chapter>
	</part>
	<part id="future-directions">
		<title>Research Projects</title>
		<partintro>
			<para>
				There are areas where further questions should be asked
				to get a better picture of what is happening out in the
				field
			</para>
		</partintro>
		<chapter id="Who-are-our-learners">
			<title>Who are our learners?</title>
			<para>
				Before we really know what system to implement we need
				to know more about our learners. It is not enough to
				have an analysis of the student demographics but also of
				the way they learn and the way they relate to
				technology.
			</para>
			<para>
				How do the studies in generational learning apply to our
				students? We are dealing with several generations of
				students and they each learn differently, how can we
				leverage those learning styles in our Distance Education
				programs?
			</para>
		</chapter>
		<chapter id="defining-distance-learning">
			<title>Defining Distance Learning</title>
			<para>
				In analyzing the responses to the survey there seems to
				be as many definitions of Distance Learning as there are
				institutions with Distance Learning programs. There are
				some commonalities; for example, all programs serve
				remote students and most, if not all, programs have a
				mediated component be it video conference, synchronous
				online meetings or asynchronous online discussions but
				is there a working definition of "Distance Learning"?
				And if there is, then is the definition the same as that
				of "e/E-Learning"?
			</para>
			<para>
				A future area of research may include searching for
				working definitions of Distance Learning and
				consolidating them into one coherent definition of what
				Distance Learning is. This should help in program
				definition and technology adoption.
			</para>
		</chapter>
		<chapter id="synchronous-versus-asynchronous">
			<title>
				Synchronous versus Asynchronous Distance Learning
			</title>
			<para>
				A large number of respondents indicated that their
				Distance Learning program was delivered asynchronously
				and therefore the survey did not apply to their
				situation. While we are only interested in synchronous
				tools for this particular survey we may want to follow
				up with those institutions who chose an asynchronous
				delivery model to ask these questions:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						What drove the adoption of an asynchronous
						Distance Learning program?
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						What criteria was used in selecting asynchronous
						versus synchronous Distance Learning delivery?
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>How long ago was the decision made?</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Would the decision change with currently
						available tools?
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para />
		</chapter>
		<chapter id="tools-and-technologies">
			<title>Available tools and technologies</title>
			<para>
				As mentioned in the rationale section of this report,
				video and technologies applicable to Distance Learning
				have progressed tremendously in the last few years. New
				offerings both in the higher education and corporate
				markets have been offered since CSU, Chico decided to
				run what has evolved into Wimba Classroom.
			</para>
			<para>
				What other tools are there that may be used to
				complement and supplement synchronous Distance Learning
				offerings? CSU, Chico currently uses Wimba Voice Tools
				for some audio-only synchronous activities. What other
				tools are available in the Market? How can we deploy
				these tools to better support a hybrid in-class and
				fully online model?
			</para>
			<para>
				Authoring tools have also made progress in the last few
				years. Tools like Trivantis Lectora and Wimba Create are
				now available in the market. These tools allow for easy
				creation of content, either directly from Microsoft Word
				like the Wimba solution or from an intuitive interface
				like Lectora's. If this facilitates the work of faculty
				we should take a look at these tools and see if they can
				be implemented on campus
			</para>
			<para>
				Simulation and demonstration tools are another area that
				is worth exploring. Tools like Adobe Captivate and
				Techsmith's Camtasia are available for purchase or
				licensing. They both allow users to create simulations
				or narrated guides using a computer interface that is
				already familiar to the user and that should facilitate
				the learning process by providing means to engage the
				content through different learning styles and at their
				leisure. Furthermore, the same technology can be used to
				provide additional activities for on-campus courses.
			</para>
			<para>
				Further research should investigate how these new tools
				interact with each other and with our Learning
				Management System (LMS); how does the content authored
				with these tools display and interacts with the LMS and
				with each other.
			</para>

			<para>
				We should investigate what tools are available for
				synchronous Distance Learning not just because the time
				is coming to evaluate new technologies for adoption but
				also because we need to be able to articulate to our
				constituents what is available to them and how we can
				expect to interact with new technologies.
			</para>

			<table xml:id="list-of-tools" rules="all" frame="box">
				<title>Sample of Available Tools</title>
				<tbody>
					<tr>
						<td>
							<emphasis role="strong">
								Name of Tool
							</emphasis>
						</td>
						<td>
							<emphasis role="strong">Website</emphasis>
						</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Softchalk</td>
						<td>http://www.softchalk.com</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Lectora</td>
						<td>http://www.trivantis.com</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>ReadyGo</td>
						<td>http://www.readygo.com</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Articulate</td>
						<td>http://www.articulate.com</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>ToolBox</td>
						<td>http://www.toolbox.com</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Smart Builder</td>
						<td>http://www.suddenlysmart.com</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Adobe Captivate</td>
						<td>
							http://www.adobe.com/products/captivate/
						</td>
					</tr>
					<tr>
						<td>Camtasia</td>
						<td>http://www.techsmith.com/camtasia.asp</td>
					</tr>
				</tbody>
			</table>
		</chapter>
		<chapter id="scorm-ims-content-sharing">
			<title>
				Learning Objects, SCORM, IMS and content sharing
			</title>
			<para>
				Research should be conducted both on the cultural change
				needed for sharing to work across the institution and
				the technologies and tools used to actually author and
				share the content.
			</para>
			<para>
				Learning Objects, some times called Reusable Learning
				Objects, are small chunks of content that can be reused
				in multiple instances and in multiple modalities. For
				more definitions of learning objects see
				<xref linkend="IEEE">IEEE,</xref>
				<xref linkend="Shepherd">Shepherd</xref>
				and
				<xref linkend="Wiley 2000">Wiley 2000</xref>
			</para>
			<para>
				<acronym>SCORM</acronym>
				(Shareable Content Object Reference Model) is a standard
				initially developed by the aviation industry as a way to
				facilitate the sharing of content among different
				vendors and in different modalities. You can build your
				content just as a series of linked HTML pages or as
				complex as a self-contained unit with quizzes,
				interactivity and ongoing feedback for the learner.
			</para>
			<para>
				Faculty can use all the tools listed in
				<xref linkend="list-of-tools" />
				can be used to to author SCORM content or the content
				package can be created manually. We no longer have to
				develop content multiple times but can "build once, use
				anywhere". Furthermore you can move these SCORM packages
				from Blackboard to Moodle or Desire2Learn making
				system-wide collaboration possible and desirable.
			</para>
			<para>
				Collaboration in terms of developing SCORM materials can
				be as simple as developing HTML or Flash content or as
				complex as assembling the SCORM package manually if it's
				needed.
			</para>
			<para>
				IMS Global Consortium a family of educational technology
				specifications developed to promote the use of computers
				in education and the interoperability of LMS and other
				eLearning tools.
			</para>
			<para>3 standard that are worth mentioning are:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong">
							Content Packaging:
						</emphasis>
						allows multiple content items to be packaged
						together and imported into an LMS or to a CD-ROM
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong">
							Quiz and Test Interoperability (QTI):
						</emphasis>
						allows quizzes and surveys to be packaged and
						shared among multiple courses across LMS
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong">
							Common Cartridge:
						</emphasis>
						still under development the common cartridge
						appears to be an aggregation of multiple course
						elements that can be ported to environments
						other than where they were created
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>

			<para>
				Learning objects are not easy to develop and they
				require a lot of planning and development time but, if
				enough objects can be created the school should see a
				significant reduction in cost for subsequent terms as
				the objects no longer need to be re-created and can be
				reused.
			</para>
			<sect1 id="building-scorm">
				<title>Building IMS and SCORM content</title>
				<para>
					Even though we can use a variety of tools to create
					IMS and SCORM content it still pays to know how to
					create the manifest XML file since we are likely to
					modify it to better suit our needs as designers and
					technical experts
				</para>
				<example>
					<title>IMS Manifest Example</title>
					<!-- Insert example1.xml here before publishing -->
				</example>
				<!-- 
					<para>
					By changing the elements in the sample file above,
					we can create content that is truly reusable accross
					LMS platforms and enable to create real
					collaboration among interested parties.
					</para>
				-->
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="cultural-change">
				<title>Creating a sharing culture</title>
				<para>
					While there are departments and institutions that
					already use and share content across courses and
					accross insturctors, for the most part we are still
					on the island model. We still support individual
					instructors
				</para>
<!-- 
			<para>
				So far instructors at CSU, Chico have developed content
				as islands with individual faculty members developing
				content that will only be used on their classes and no
				one else's. This has lead to duplication of work.
			</para>

 -->			</sect1>
		</chapter>
		<chapter id="tool-accessibility">
			<title>Tool Accessibility</title>
			<subtitle>
				Defining a standard way to test tools for accessibility
			</subtitle>
			<para></para>
			<sect1 id="tool-accessibility-intro">
				<title>Introduction</title>
				<para>
					While there has been an emphasis in web
					accessibility for websites and the retrofitting of
					existing web content there hasn't been a consistent
					effort to test content creation tools for their
					creation of accessible content and how accessible
					the tools themselves are.
				</para>
				<para>
					This project seeks to address these issues by
					providing both a methodology and a selection of
					tools to test. It also seeks to create awareness
					regarding testing methodologies and how they can be
					applied to evaluating technology.
				</para>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="problem-statement">
				<title>Problem Statement</title>
				<para>
					Each California State University campus usses it own
					set of tools to develop content for their online
					delivery. In the past it was ok to use an HTML
					editor such as Adobe DreamWeaver to create content.
					Now faculty want immediate results and don't care as
					much about the underlying technology that allows to
					create content but want the content to be created
					with minimal effort and maximum results.
				</para>
				<para>
					Students expectations have also evolved over the
					years. Where it was OK to just convert a Word
					Document to HTML now students want better quality on
					their instructional materials.
				</para>
				<para>
					There are several tools available to help faculty in
					developing content both for their LMS content as
					well as for their web-based content. A sample of the
					tools is listed below:
				</para>
				<informaltable xml:id="list-of-tools-aaccessibility"
					rules="all" frame="box">
					<tbody>
						<tr>
							<td>
								<emphasis role="strong">
									Name of Tool
								</emphasis>
							</td>
							<td>
								<emphasis role="strong">
									Website
								</emphasis>
							</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Softchalk</td>
							<td>http://www.softchalk.com</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Lectora</td>
							<td>http://www.trivantis.com</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>ReadyGo</td>
							<td>http://www.readygo.com</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Articulate</td>
							<td>http://www.articulate.com</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>ToolBox</td>
							<td>http://www.toolbox.com</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Smart Builder</td>
							<td>http://www.suddenlysmart.com</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Adobe Captivate</td>
							<td>
								http://www.adobe.com/products/captivate/
							</td>
						</tr>
						<tr>
							<td>Camtasia</td>
							<td>
								http://www.techsmith.com/camtasia.asp
							</td>
						</tr>
					</tbody>
				</informaltable>
				<para>
					I am not aware at this time whether any studies
					beyond the vendors' claims of compliance that
					confirm or refute the vendors claims. This project
					seeks to provide an initial knowledge base regarding
					content creation tools accessibility and as a
					springboard for Universities to select their tools
					knowing that they are accessible
				</para>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="accessibility-methodology">
				<title>Methodology</title>
				<para>
					To avoid upsetting the balance at each other a
					survey will be conducted to determine which, if any,
					authoring tools are being used by each. This will
					provide an initial list of tools to evaluate.
				</para>
				<para>
					Sample content authored in Microsoft Word 2003 and
					Microsoft Word 2007 will be input into each of the
					tools selected. The content will then be evaluated
					ussing standard accessibility tools.
				</para>
				<para>
					In a parallel evaluation track the tools themselves
					will be evaluated for accessibility using JAWS
				</para>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="results">
				<title>Results</title>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="conclusions">
				<title>Conclusions</title>
			</sect1>
		</chapter>
	</part>
	<part id="cases">
		<title>Case Studies</title>
		<partintro>
			<para>
				The following chapters describe case studies in the use
				of technology in higher education. They are all over the
				place and that's intentional: Technology in higher
				education should be varied and should challenge our
				assumptions and make us question our vision for our
				programs and the technologies that we use
			</para>
			<para>
				The first chapter in this section describes the CSU
				Moodle Coalition, a collaborative effort from 3 CSU
				campuses in their Moodle efforts. It seeks to understand
				the choices the coalition members have made in the
				research implementation and now in their enterprise
				characteristics of their joint system
			</para>
		</partintro>
		<chapter id="moodle-case">
			<title>The Moodle experience</title>
			<subtitle>Looking at Open Source for an LMS</subtitle>
			<sect1 id="moodle-intro-history">
				<title>Introduction and Background</title>
				<para>
					Moodle (
					<link xlink:href="http://www.moodle.org">
						http://www.moodle.org
					</link>
					) has always been an interesting alternative in the
					LMS competition, dominated by WebCT and Blackboard
					until the later acquired WebCT in 2006. With recent
					changes in the system wide procurement of LMS
					software people are starting to look at Moodle as a
					viable alternative to the big commercial LMS vendors
					in an Open Source Format.
				</para>
				<para>
					Three CSU campuses are the leaders in implementing
					Moodle across the CSU: Humboldt State University,
					San Francisco State University and California State
					University, Monterey Bay. They have formed a
					Coalition to better support their development effort
					with Moodle.
				</para>
				<para>
					Moodle itself has proved suprisingly popular since
					it was first released by Martin Dougiamas, an LMS
					administrator for an Australian University in
					August, 2002. Moodle, as many other Open Source
					projects, has developed a strong and healthy
					community around the LMS; this community provides
					for a support mechanism where the bugs are solved
					much quicker than in a propietary solution where
					they go through a close development process and a QA
					process where none of the customers get to see the
					work being done, only the results. In Moodle, the
					bugs are reported openly and there are multiple
					developers engaged in the process of supporting the
					community and fixing any bugs that may appear.
				</para>
				<para>
					There is also the perceived cost of Moodle versus
					propietary software. While it is true that the
					license itself is considerably cheaper there are
					additional costs that are not always factored into
					this equation. You can choose to use Moodle and any
					Open Source software as is or "out of the box" with
					just a minimal knowledge of PHP, SQL databases and
					HTML and live with the limitations that the software
					may have for your particular institutional needs. Or
					you can choose to custmoize and enchance Moodle
					which means that you need one or more programmers
					who are experts in developing web applications in
					PHP, who have knowledge of web application
					architecture and who can dedicate significant time
					to developing the applications and functionality
					needed by the individual institution.
				</para>
				<para>
					Either option entails risks and bennefits. In
					exploring how the 3 universities in the consortium
					dealt with this problems and others, we also explore
					how these problems may be answered at out
					institutions, either as part of the Moodle Coalition
					or idependently.
				</para>
				<para>
					Moodle has also spawned several for-profit
					commercial groups that provide services beyond those
					the Moodle community can offer. One of these
					commercial support companies is Moodlerooms (
					<link xlink:href="http://www.moodlerooms.com/">
						http://www.moodlerooms.com/
					</link>
					) whose western regional office is headed by a
					former Humboldt State University staff member.
					According to their website, Moodlerooms offers the
					following services to the Moodle community:
				</para>
				<blockquote>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								solutions: Moodlerooms provides a wide
								range of hosting/bandwidth packages
								powered by Sun Microsystems. From
								individual users to institutions with
								tens of thousands of users, we can
								securely host your Moodle LMS.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								implementation/Integration Services:
								Moodlerooms can write the customization
								code that will tie Moodle into your
								information infrastructure.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Instruction/Training Services:
								Moodlerooms offers online and onsite
								training for Moodle instructors. A blend
								of instruction will give your
								instructors the skills and deliverables
								to run their own Moodle courses.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Moodle Mentor Services: Experienced
								Moodlers guide our clients through
								pedagogical and technical questions
								concerning Moodle. The Moodle Mentor
								subscription is one year of support
								couched in a community of Moodle
								instructors.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Customization Services: Ever dreamed of
								a new feature? With open-source code and
								a development team, Moodlerooms can
								shape Moodle to better match your needs
								and vision. (
								<xref linkend="moodlerooms">
									Moodlerooms
								</xref>
								)
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</blockquote>
				<para>
					The result of this combination of strong community
					and knowledgeable commercial support presents a
					challenge in the
				</para>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="individual-histories">
				<title>Where each school was</title>
				<para></para>
				<!-- 
					Questions to ask:	
					* How long ago did you start using Moodle? 
					* What software did you use before?
					* What influenced your decision to research and eventually switch to new LMS?
					* Who was your campus' champion in the adoption process
					
					<sect2 id="humboldt-history">
					<title>Humboldt State</title>
					<para></para>
					</sect2>
					<sect2 id="sfsu-history">
					<title>San Fracisco State</title>
					<para></para>
					</sect2>
					<sect2 id="csumb-history">
					<title>
					California State University, Monterey Bay
					</title>
					<para></para>
					</sect2>
				-->
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="decision-making-process">
				<title>The Decisionmaking Process</title>
				<para></para>
				<!-- 
					Questions to ask:
					* Was moodle your only choice when transitioning from your Commercial LMS?
					** If not what other software did you look at?
					* Who was in the decision making group? Was this a normal group within the school's governance system?
					* How did the group arrive to the finalist? was there a rubric?
					* What other institutions, if any, did you communicate with during the selection process?
					** What was their feedback?
					
					<sect2 id="humboldt-decision">
					<title>Humboldt State</title>
					<para></para>
					</sect2>
					<sect2 id="sfsu-decision">
					<title>San Fracisco State</title>
					<para></para>
					</sect2>
					<sect2 id="csumb-decision">
					<title>
					California State University, Monterey Bay
					</title>
					<para></para>
					</sect2>
				-->
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="implementation">
				<title>Implementing Moodle</title>
				<para></para>
				<!-- 
					<sect2 id="humboldt-implementation">
					<title>Humboldt State</title>
					<para></para>
					</sect2>
					<sect2 id="sfsu-implementation">
					<title>San Fracisco State</title>
					<para></para>
					</sect2>
					<sect2 id="csumb-implementation">
					<title>
					California State University, Monterey Bay
					</title>
					<para></para>
					</sect2>
				-->
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="coalition-building">
				<title>Building the Coalition</title>
				<para></para>
				<!-- 
					Questions to ask:
					* What drove the campuses to form a coalition?
					* What are the individual members contributing to the coalition?
					* What accomplishments do you think best exemplify the work of the coalition?
					* What are the benefits expected out of the coalition?
				-->
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="the-future">
				<title>Looking forward</title>
				<para></para>
				<!-- 
					Questions to ask:
					Open depending on the answers to the other areas
				-->
			</sect1>
		</chapter>
	</part>
	<part id="in-closing">
		<title>Reflections and predictions</title>
		<partintro>
			<para>
				The following chapters are the conclusion of the themes
				covered earlier in this book. They address predictions
				of where we are going with technology itself, where we
				should be going with a Distance Learning program and
				where should our research emphasis be.
			</para>
			<blockquote>
				<para>
					<emphasis role="strong">
						More so than any other portion of this book,
						these chapters are my opinion and most
						definitely do not reflect those of CSU, Chico or
						the CSU system.
					</emphasis>
				</para>
			</blockquote>
		</partintro>
		<chapter id="ideal-distance-learning-program">
			<title>
				Vision and mission for a Distance Learning program
			</title>
			<subtitle>
				What I think a Distance Learning program should be
			</subtitle>
			<para>
				Based on all the research contained in the previous
				chapters what should a Distance Learning Program look
				like? What elements should we incorporate into this
				program? and, more importantly, how should we prepare
				such a program for the challenges ahead? In
				<xref linkend="program-addie" />
				I will provide a generic framework for analysis.
				Afterwards I will add additional considerations that
				don't really fit into the ADDIE model.
			</para>
			<para>
				There are a few assumptions built into this model:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong">
							Personel working in this project are
							generalist with an area of emphasis or
							interest:
						</emphasis>
						While it's ok for people to manifest their
						preferences and interests, there is no reason
						for a request not to be completed because people
						are not familiar with policies and procedures be
						them technical or pedagogical.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong">
							Where possible, staff are exclusively
							assigned to the Distance Learning project:
						</emphasis>
						I understand that this is unrealistic and that
						people usually take on, or are assigned, more
						than they should. However people working on a
						Distance Learning program should make that the
						emphasis of their work with other considerations
						being secondary to the Distance Learning effort
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong">
							There is a set of tools and technologies
							that the team has agreed to support:
						</emphasis>
						I am the first one to admit that I get
						distracted with the greatest and latest
						technology. But if we're going to provide
						program-wide support then we must agree on the
						technologies we are going to support.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong">
							There is a committment to the success of the
							team over individual achievements:
						</emphasis>
						I will never discount the importance of
						individual success and satisfaction as long as
						it is not at the expense of the team's success
						and the overall mission of the Distance Learning
						program.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong">
							If any changes are to be made to an existing
							program they need to be agreed upon by the
							entire team
						</emphasis>
						rather than implemented unilaterally by one
						member of the team.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<sect1 id="program-addie">
				<title>Systematic Program Development</title>
				<para>
					In order to develop a consistent Distance Learning
					program we need a systematic framework. I have
					chosen the ADDIE model to use as my design framework
					for a variety of reasons: it is the design model I
					am most familiar with; the steps in the process as
					familiar to most designers and they provide a
					framework that is easy to follow.
				</para>
				<sect2 id="addie-analysis">
					<title>Analysis and Selection</title>
					<para>
						Where we are and where we need to be are the
						first 2 questions that need to be asked. They
						seem easy questions to ask but the answers can
						be complicated.
					</para>
					<para>
						The
						<emphasis>where are are</emphasis>
						question depends on who we ask. Students,
						faculty and administrators are likely to have
						different opinions on what the issues and
						solutions are. In order to get a better picture
						of what the program should really be like we
						should merge the opinions from each of the
						constituents groups; what may be acceptable for
						faculty may not be acceptable for students and
						vice versa. Perhaps qualifying the opinions of
						each group and listing them in numerical order
						(how many people expressed the same opinion)
					</para>
					<para>
						I don't like surveying people unless it is
						deemed the best way to obtain information but in
						this situation a survey would be the best way to
						collect information about opinions and attitudes
						regarding the current program. If needed the
						survey can be followed up with targeted
						interviews to follow up on specific issues. This
						would allow us to collect aggregate data from
						our target population and only follow up with
						interviews where the survey data generated
						additional questions.
					</para>
					<para>
						Knowing where we are today will allow us to
						better answer the question
						<emphasis>where we need to be.</emphasis>
						In analzying where we are going we need to
						consider the needs assessment from a pedagogical
						as well as a technical perspective. It is not
						only necessary to know what tools we should be
						using; we also need a solid pedagogical
						foundation as to why we will be using the tools
						we have chosen to support in the ways we are
						proposing to use them.
					</para>
					<para>
						Those challenges that I consider most important
						from those posed by James L. Morrison and his
						team at the University of North Carolina, Chapel
						Hill (
						<xref linkend="Horizon">Horizon</xref>
						) have been highlighted in the lists below. It
						may be the case that these challenges are no
						longer relevant, that's for the team to decide.
						It does, however, raise interesting policy
						questions for any Distance Learning program.
						Some of the challenges and questions they posed:
					</para>
					<para>Instructional Challenges</para>
					<blockquote>
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									What topics lend themselves to
									distance education?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How can we create a community of
									online learners?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we maximize student-teacher,
									student-student interaction online?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we accommodate different
									learning styles and age ranges?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we set appropriate
									expectations for student work?
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
					</blockquote>
					<para>Management Challenges</para>
					<blockquote>
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									What training do faculty members
									need to be successful in online
									teaching?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we provide equal access to
									distance learning?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									What funding models should we adapt
									to support distance learning course
									development (cost-benefit analysis)?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we educate the decision
									makers on technology support?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we ascertain the goals of
									distance learning (efficiency, broad
									standards, access to quality
									education, reaching broader group of
									learners)?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How can we support the delivery of
									online education (e.g.,
									registration, advising, library and
									laboratory facilities)?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									What intellectual
									properties/copyright issues must be
									addressed?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we deal with the system when
									it fails?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we address privacy issues?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we address the
									respectability/image of distance
									education issue?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we develop balance in
									distance learning workloads compared
									to traditional workloads in clinical
									settings?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									What is the relationship of online
									education to residential campus
									education?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we market distance education
									in a changing marketplace?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do faculty attitudes towards
									distance learning impact developing
									distance education programs?
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
					</blockquote>
					<para>Assessment Challenges</para>
					<blockquote>
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we monitor/authenticate
									student performance in distance
									learning?
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									How do we assess effectiveness of
									online learning?
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
					</blockquote>
					<para>
						We need to pay attention to what communities
						colleges are doing. Since universities get most
						of their students from community colleges it
						pays to pay attention to what they are doing in
						terms of Distance Learning. We need to prepare
						for what our students are using before they come
						to our school by either setting up their
						expectations accordingly or adopting the tools
						in use at other institutions to our processes
						and procedures. See
						<xref linkend="survey" />
						for more information
					</para>
					<para>
						We should also pay attention to the tools
						available in the commercial/business sector and
						in higher education markets other than ours and
						our peer institutions and . One of the errors I
						see made over and over is that we limit
						ourselves to the tools other colleges and
						universities are using when it is sometimes true
						that comercial developer and large companies
						with their own training groups have developed
						better and easier to use tools.
					</para>
					<para>
						One of the questions that is bound to be
						controversial is the choice between an
						empowerment and a service model.An empowerment
						model seeks to give instructors the tools
						necessary for them to complete their
						work-related projects on their own with only
						minor assistance. Service models, on the other
						hand, seek for staff to work with faculty as the
						primary developers of the content. The faculty
						is the Subject Matter Expert and the facilitator
						of the course they teach and, if they so choose,
						can collaborate with the development of the
						material but they are not expected to.
					</para>
					<para>
						This discussion between empowerment and service
						becomes important when we set faculty's
						expectations and a Service Level Agreement. What
						are we expecting the faculty members, our
						primary customers, to do for themselves and what
						are we ready and willing to do for them?
					</para>
					<para>
						Clear expectations are your friends when you're
						part of a project team. They clear the waters
						and they help to clarify any sort of confusion
						when it comes to who is supposed to do what. Use
						the force, young project team member, use the
						force and your SLA.
					</para>
					<sect3>
						<title>
							Desing &amp; Selection Deliverables
						</title>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="strong">
								Deliverables at this stage:
							</emphasis>
						</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Analysis document containing results
									of faculty, student and
									administration surveys.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									List of technologies to be evaluated
									and implemented. Preferably ranked
									in order of importance.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									List of improvements to current
									processes and procedures along with
									new ideas on how to run operations
									and support faculty.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									A rubric to use when selecting the
									tools to be used in the program.
									Ideally we should have one rubric
									for each area of the program we are
									implementing
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</sect3>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="addie-design-development">
					<title>Design &amp; Development</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							Be careful what you wish for.... You may get
							it.
						</caption>
						<alt>
							Be careful what you wish for.... You may get
							it. Dilbert cartoon
						</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5.5in"
								format="GIF" fileref="./images/dilbert22444920080310.gif" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para>
								Be careful what you wish for.... You may
								get it. Dilbert cartoon
							</para>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						Designing a program is different and more
						challenging than developing tools but it
						includes processes, procedures and the tools
						that we need to implement these new programs.
					</para>
					<para>
						Before we start work on designing and developing
						strategies for working on our new system, we
						need to, as a team, develop our mission
						statement. What we are about, what we seek to
						accomplish and the steps we will take to
						accomplish these objectives. Vision goes hand in
						hand with mission; while the mission statement
						talks about specific objectives, the mission
						talks about over-arching goals, what are the
						global things that we want to accomplish with
						the program and how will the mission, the people
						and the technology will help us get there.
					</para>
					<para>
						The first step in deciding what the program is
						going to look like is to select the tools that
						we will use in this program. How do the tools we
						are looking at align with the mission statement;
						for example: How will the tools we are selecting
						will facilitate faculty's work on their online
						courses? This is where the rubrics developed as
						part of the analysis and selection process need
						to be used by selection committee with
						participation of all our constituents: students,
						faculty, technical staff and administrators.
						Under no circumstance should anything be done
						without faculty and administration input. For an
						example of what a tool selection process might
						look like, see
						<xref linkend="tool-accessibility" />
						.
					</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<emphasis>
									What happens if none of the tools we
									propose are chosen by the committee?
								</emphasis>
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								<emphasis>
									What happens if the committee
									chooses more than 1 tool in a given
									category where the team was hoping
									to have only 1 chosen?
								</emphasis>
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>
						Hopefully this won't happen but the team needs
						to be prepared to address concerns like the ones
						above and others that may be raised over time.
						The team needs to establish a system were
						constituents communicate issues and concerns
						but, at the same time, they should establish a
						timeline with deadlines after which elements of
						the program are set and can no longer be
						changed.
					</para>
					<para>
						Once the tools are decided on training, support
						and operational plans need to be designed and
						developed. These training interventions, in
						whatever form they take, should as close as
						possible to be delivered to potential customers.
						Care should be taken in developing multiple
						modalities of training for faculty. Long gone
						are the days where face-to-face instructor led
						training was the only realistic way to deliver
						training for faculty. Now it's becoming more and
						more usual to hear faculty requesting Just In
						Time training, consultations and tutorials to
						get help when and how they need it.
					</para>
					<para>
						Support models to be implemented need to take
						into account the fact that programs being run
						have users from diverse geographical areas
						attending the same classes. The fact that there
						is not really a set schedule for attending the
						class present new challenges for a support team.
					</para>
					<para>
						One area that has gained importance in the past
						couple years is accessibility. With Section 508,
						state and institutional mandates on
						accessibility it has become essential to both
						make old content accessible and to incorporate
						accessibility into all instructional material.
						How do we support accessibility from the
						beginning rather than have to retrofit content
						when needed? This is the time to develop an
						initial accessibility plan and discuss it with
						the campus accessibility and disabled student
						support team.
					</para>
					<para>
						New operational models are needed to support
						these new technologies. How to use, run and
						support the software the team has selected to
						use and support. Processes need to be developed
						in, at least, three different areas: faculty
						support, student support and escalation to
						vendor. Any additional areas of support should
						be addressed at this point.
					</para>
					<para>
						Encourage the team to develop multiple
						approaches to address these issues. Multiple
						perspectives are healthy and will encourage
						debate regarding best practices. It may also
						cover blind spots that may have been overlooked.
						It should not turn into a competition regarding
						whose approaches are better suited for a
						particular situation, that's for the team to
						decide. Nor should it turn into a personality
						conflict waiting to explode.
					</para>
					<para>
						Communication is critical throughout the process
						but particularly so at the design and
						development stages. I am not partial to
						meetings. For the most part they are poorly run
						and become ground for the airing personal issues
						to the detriment of the team and the specific
						goals the team is pursuing. That is not to say
						that team meetings are not useful, when properly
						run and with the proper motivation.
						<xref linkend="Lopp 2007">Lopp (2007)</xref>
						lists some of the good and not-so-good qualities
						of brainstorming and design meetings:
					</para>
					<blockquote>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Are decisions being made? Is the
									group working well enough to make a
									decision? Yes? Good.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Are decisions being revisited? Is
									the group limber enough to go
									backwards to refine a previous
									decision? Even better.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Are decisions constantly being
									revisited? Ok, problem here. Your
									team has spun into creative nirvana.
									A good time to step back and apply a
									little structure to the process.
									Reviewing decisions to date is a
									good way to find structure and move
									forward. Oh, you weren’t writing
									down the results of brainstorm
									meetings? Ooops. Start now.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Are basic truths about your design
									showing up? These are the gems of
									brainstorm. These are decisions
									which are made that define the basic
									design of your problem. You’ll know
									these when they show up, stand up to
									scrutiny, and eventually starting
									virally wandering the hallways.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Are holy shit moments occurring?
									Similar to the basic truth
									discovery, but louder and
									infrequent. "HOLY SHIT, we're
									completely wrong." Holy shits are
									disruptive, but are a good sign a
									limber creative process.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Is the to do list growing or
									shrinking? If you’re early on in the
									design phase, it should be growing.
									If you’re getting close to the end
									of your design phase, it better be
									getting smaller.... Better is the
									enemy of done and if it’s your
									project, you need to draw a line on
									what topics/ideas you intend to
									tackle and stick to it.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</blockquote>
					<para>
						The twin qualities of a meeting are creativity
						and accountability. It is not enough to expect
						or demand creativity. The team needs to be
						accountable to administration and to our
						constituents. We have to remain flexible to deal
						with changes and the only way to do that is by
						having a thinking team. One that can react when
						the situation demands, but also a team that
						retains the capability of think a problem
						through, either as it's happening or afterwards
						as it is debriefed. The best way to put it is in
						the quote below:
					</para>
					<blockquote>
						<para>
							... but Google gets two wins out of the
							program. First, some of the projects create
							value for the company. It’s probably one in
							five, but that’s not the real value. Google
							is creating a culture of thinking by
							allowing their employees to wander about and
							bump into shit.
						</para>
						<para>
							I don’t know what you do and I don’t know
							what you build. I am certain that if you
							don’t demonstrate creative thinking in what
							you build, you’re screwed because you, your
							team, and your product will stagnate.
							Kicking off brainstorming meetings are a
							tricky proposition. They are poorly defined,
							hard to run, and harder to measure. What
							comes out of these meetings might be
							brilliance or stupidity… the difference
							between the two is magnificently slim. Good
							luck. (
							<xref linkend="Lopp 2007">Lopp 2007</xref>
							)
						</para>
					</blockquote>
					<para>
						Once we have all our training developeed and our
						procedures in place it is time to run a pilot.
						This pilot should be kept small; we are
						evaluating our training, policies, procedures
						and support systems, not releasing the program
						to the whole world. I'd reccomend anywhere for 5
						to 8 faculty members teaching 1 course section
						each at most for an initial program.
					</para>
					<para>
						I include a pilot during the design and
						development phase because it gives us time to
						make changes without impacting our timeline too
						much. It is the iterative nature of the program.
						We tested something and then we make any changes
						to the elements of the program based on the
						results of the test. This is also different than
						a pilot run during the implementation phase.
						They are both testing different areas of the
						program and should be treated accordingly
					</para>
					<para></para>
					<sect3 id="design-development-deliverables">
						<title>
							Design &amp; Development Deliverables
						</title>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="strong">
								Deliverables at this stage:
							</emphasis>
						</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Vision and mission statements for
									the program
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Documents indicating initial
									workflow, processes and procedures
									to support faculty and students
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Document outlining processes,
									procedures and workflows to escalate
									issues to vendors
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Internal communication workflows and
									protocols
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Basic training workshops sketched
									and delivered at least once to a
									pilot group
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</sect3>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="addie-implementation">
					<title>Implementation</title>
					<blockquote>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="strong">
								There's never time to do it right but
								there's always time to do it over
							</emphasis>
						</para>
					</blockquote>
					<para>
						Once we have the blueprints created during the
						design and development stages it is now time to
						get busy with implementing the policies,
						procedures and systems we need to have in place
						for our second pilot run.
					</para>
					<para>
						Training should be taking its final form by now;
						mostly polish and changes based on feedback from
						pilot training participants. We need to make
						sure that training in its final form is ready to
						go when we first start soliciting instructors
						for our large pilot and formative evaluation.
					</para>
					<para>
						As training solidifies, the policy and
						procedures aspect should also be finalized. The
						team should be spending time fleshing out the
						training outlines and to begin in depth
						conversations with any group that interacts with
						them in any capacity to make sure that "we are
						all in the same page." There is nothing worst
						than having your very carefully thought out plan
						nixed by an outside group because it involves
						too much work from their end without a
						significant return on investment.
					</para>
					<para>
						Once we call implementation done we should be
						looking at finished products; fully agreed upon
						processes and procedures and line of
						communications ready and available for two-way
						communication with all our stake holders;
						training in its final form (or as final as
						training ever gets).
					</para>
					<sect3 id="implementation-deliverables">
						<title>Implementation Deliverables</title>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="strong">
								Deliverables at this stage:
							</emphasis>
						</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Documents indicating final workflow,
									processes and procedures to support
									faculty and students
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Document outlining final processes,
									procedures and workflows to escalate
									issues to vendors
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Internal communication workflows and
									protocols agreed upon by the team
									and those stake holders directly
									involved in supporting Distance
									Learning
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Final training workshops
									incorporating the feedback from the
									training pilot group
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</sect3>
				</sect2>
				<sect2 id="addie-evaluation">
					<title>Evaluation</title>
					<mediaobject>
						<caption>
							The customer is always right, is he?
						</caption>
						<alt>The customer is always right, is he?</alt>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata align="center" width="5.5in"
								format="GIF" fileref="./images/uf006179.gif" />
						</imageobject>
						<textobject>
							<para>
								The customer is always right, is he?.
								User Friendly web comic strip
							</para>
						</textobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						From my perspective there is no better tool than
						evaluation for program improvement. The feedback
						we gather from our constitutents and
						stakeholders is the best way to keep a pulse on
						the team's status and overall program health.
					</para>
					<para>
						I also want to emphasize the differences between
						the formative and summative evaluations:
						Formative evaluations test policies, procedures
						and workflows while summative evaluation seeks
						feedback on the program itself.
					</para>
					<para>
						It is only through this combination of feedback
						gathered periodically that we can hope to have a
						competitive distance learning program.
					</para>
					<sect3 id="addie-formative-evaluation">
						<title>Formative Evaluations</title>
						<para>
							I am a strong believer in continual
							improvement and rapid prototyping
						</para>
						<para>
							Continual improvement means that we're never
							really done with a project; periodically we
							evaluate the current status of the project
							and make changes according to the evaluation
							results.
						</para>
						<para>
							Rapid Prototyping (
							<xref linkend="Tripp &amp; Bichelmeyer" />
							) proposes an iterative design where the
							phase of design, development and
							implementation in the ADDIE model are
							accelerated in order for the audience to
							provide feedback over a completed product
							and additional iterations of a project as
							needed to correct problems found by the
							feedback providers.
						</para>
						<para>
							The different aspects of the project need to
							be evaluated by all constituents: faculty,
							students and support staff. The main
							difference between these evaluation groups
							is how often does the team solicit their
							feedback. Faculty and students' feedback
							should be solicited, at least, once a
							semester or academic term. This will allow
							the team to provide continual improvement to
							our customers
						</para>
						<para>
							Formative evaluation from the technical and
							support staffs should happen as often as
							needed to maintain proper operation. I would
							suggest weekly to start and move on to
							bi-weekly or even montly if the traffic
							slows down enough. It is important not to
							stop the feedback look just becasue there
							are no problems.
						</para>
					</sect3>
					<sect3 id="addie-summative-evaluation">
						<title>Summative Evaluations</title>
						<para>
							Summative evaluations tend to not to be
							conducted as often as the formative
							evaluations. I also call these occurrences
							"program reviews" where project staff,
							faculty and administration gather together
							to evaluate the program and
							suggest/propose/demand changes.
						</para>
						<para>
							A well run program review meeting or
							meetings (I think this process should be
							done over time) is to modify the program as
							needed to
						</para>
					</sect3>
					<sect3 id="evaluation-deliverables">
						<title>Evaluation Deliverables</title>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="strong">
								Deliverables at this stage:
							</emphasis>
						</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Formative Evaluation rubrics for
									student, faculty
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Meeting schedule for formative
									evaluation from technical and
									support staff
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para></para>
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</sect3>
				</sect2>
			</sect1>
			<sect1 id="further-thoughts-and-ideas">
				<title>Further thoughts and ideas</title>
				<para></para>
			</sect1>
		</chapter>
		<chapter id="general-conclusions">
			<title>General Conclusions</title>
			<subtitle>
				Where I go out on a limb to make predictions as to where
				we are going
			</subtitle>
			<para>
				I'd like to frame this randomness with something I
				caught from Twitter:
			</para>
			<blockquote>
				<para>
					What kind of technologically mediated/enhanced tasks
					will our students face in five years and how are we
					preparing them (or not)?
				</para>
				<para>Chris Lott about 1h ago via web</para>
			</blockquote>
			<para></para>
		</chapter>

	</part>
	<bibliography id="bibliography">
		<title>Further Reading</title>
		<para />
		<bibliodiv>
			<title>eLearning and Distance Learning</title>
			<para></para>

			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Brandon 2007'
				xml:id='Brandon 2007'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<editor>Brandon, B. (Editor)</editor>
					(2007)
					<title role='book'>
						The eLearning Guild's Handbook of eLearning
						Strategy.
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Santa Rosa, CA.
					<publishername>The eLearning Guild.</publishername>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Brandon 2007a'
				xml:id='brandon 2007a'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<editor>Brandon, B. (Editor)</editor>
					(2007)
					<title role='book'>
						The eLearning Guild's Handbook of eLearning
						Strategy.
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Santa Rosa, CA.
					<publishername>The eLearning Guild.</publishername>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Cleary 2007' xml:id='Cleary 2007'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<editor>Cleary, J.</editor>
					(2007)
					<title role='book'>
						E-Learning 101: An Introduction to E-Learning,
						Learning Tools and Technologies.
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Sunnyvale, CA.
					<publishername>
						Brandon Hall Research.
					</publishername>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Cole &amp; Robertson 2006'
				xml:id='Cole &amp; Robertson 2006'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Cole, J., and B. Robertson (2006)
					<title role='book'>
						Using Market Segmentation to Develop a Large
						Section, Web-enhanced Survey Course
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<title>Innovate</title>
					<volumenum>2</volumenum>
					<issuenum>(4)</issuenum>
					. Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link xlink:href="http://snurl.com/23mvm">
						http://snurl.com/23mvm
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Horizon' xml:id='Horizon'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Horizon Team
					<title role="book">
						Challenges in Implementing Distance Learning
						Programs
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://horizon.unc.edu/projects/resources/44items.html">
						http://horizon.unc.edu/projects/resources/44items.html
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
		</bibliodiv>
		<bibliodiv>
			<title>IMS, SCORM and Learning Objects</title>
			<para></para>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='ADL' xml:id='ADL'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Advanced Distributed Learning
					<title role="book">ADL Website</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link xlink:href="http://www.adl.org/">
						http://www.adl.org
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='IEEE' xml:id='IEEE'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					IEEE Learning Technology Standards Committee (LTSC)
					<title role='book'>
						IEEE 1484.12.1-2002, 15 July 2002, Draft
						Standard for Learning Object Metadata
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link xlink:href="http://peek.snurl.com/23drs">
						http://peek.snurl.com/23drs
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Nichani' xml:id='Nichani'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Nichani, M.
					<title role='book'>
						LCMS = LMS + CMS [RLOs] - How does this effect
						the learner? The instructional designer?
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href=" http://www.elearningpost.com/articles/archives/lcms_lms_cms_rlos/">
						http://www.elearningpost.com/articles/archives/lcms_lms_cms_rlos/
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Ostyn 2007' xml:id='Ostyn 2007'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Ostyn, C. (2007)
					<title role='book'>
						In the Eye of the SCORM: An introduction to
						SCORM 2004 for Content Developers
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://www.ostyn.com/standards/docs/Eye_Of_The_SCORM_draft.pdf">
						http://www.ostyn.com/standards/docs/Eye_Of_The_SCORM_draft.pdf
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='SCORM' xml:id='SCORM'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<title role='book'>The SCORM Blog</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link xlink:href="http://www.scormblog.com/">
						http://www.scormblog.com/
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Shepherd' xml:id='Shepherd'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Shepherd, C.
					<title role='book'>Objects of Interest</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://www.fastrak-consulting.co.uk/tactix/features/objects/objects.htm">
						http://www.fastrak-consulting.co.uk/tactix/features/objects/objects.htm
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Wiley 1999' xml:id='Wiley 1999'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Wiley, D. A. (1999)
					<title role='book'>
						The Post-LEGO Learning Object
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://opencontent.org/docs/post-lego.pdf">
						http://opencontent.org/docs/post-lego.pdf
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Wiley 2000' xml:id='Wiley 2000'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Wiley, D. A. (2000)
					<title role="book">
						Connecting learning objects to instructional
						design theory: A definition, a metaphor, and a
						taxonomy
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://reusability.org/read/chapters/wiley.doc">
						http://reusability.org/read/chapters/wiley.doc
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
		</bibliodiv>
		<bibliodiv>
			<title>Instructional Design</title>
			<para></para>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Buffington 2003'
				xml:id='Buffington 2003'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Buffington, J. (2003)
					<title role="book">
						Learning communities as an instructional model.
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					In
					<editor>M. Orey (Ed.)</editor>
					<title>
						Emerging perspectives on learning, teaching, and
						technology
					</title>
					Retrieved 3/19/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://projects.coe.uga.edu/epltt/index.php?title=Learning_Communities_as_an_Instructional_Model">
						http://projects.coe.uga.edu/epltt/index.php?title=Learning_Communities_as_an_Instructional_Model
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Forehand' xml:id='forehand'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Forehand, M. (2005)
					<title role="book">
						Bloom's taxonomy: Original and revised.
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					In
					<editor>M. Orey (Ed.)</editor>
					<title>
						Emerging perspectives on learning, teaching, and
						technology
					</title>
					Retrieved 3/19/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://projects.coe.uga.edu/epltt/index.php?title=Bloom%27s_Taxonomy">
						http://projects.coe.uga.edu/epltt/index.php?title=Bloom%27s_Taxonomy
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Galloway' xml:id='galloway'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Galloway, C. M. (2001)
					<title role="book">
						Vygotsky's Constructionism.
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					In
					<editor>M. Orey (Ed.)</editor>
					<title>
						Emerging perspectives on learning, teaching, and
						technology
					</title>
					Retrieved 3/19/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://projects.coe.uga.edu/epltt/index.php?title=Vygotsky%27s_constructivism">
						http://projects.coe.uga.edu/epltt/index.php?title=Vygotsky%27s_constructivism
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Kaufman &amp; Watkins'
				xml:id='Kaufman &amp; Watkins'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Kaufman, R. &amp; Watkins, R. (2000)
					<title role="book">
						Getting Serious About Results and Payoffs: We
						are what we say, do, and deliver.
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/19/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://www.ispi.org/services/Glossary/Kaufman_Watkin.pdf">
						http://www.ispi.org/services/Glossary/Kaufman_Watkin.pdf
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Tripp &amp; Bichelmeyer'
				xml:id='Tripp &amp; Bichelmeyer'>
				Tripp, S. D., &amp; Bichelmeyer, B. (1990).
				<bibliomset relation='article'>
					Rapid Prototyping: An alternative instructional
					design strategy
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<title>
						Educational Technology Research and Development
					</title>
					<volumenum>38</volumenum>
					<issuenum>(1)</issuenum>
					.
					<artpagenums>31 - 44</artpagenums>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Waters &amp; Gibbons'
				xml:id='Waters &amp; Gibbons'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Waters, S. &amp; Gibbons, A. (2004)
					<title role="book">
						Design Languages, Notation Systems, and
						Instructional Technology: A Case Study
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<title>
						Educational Technology Research and Development
					</title>
					<volumenum>52</volumenum>
					<issuenum>(2)</issuenum>
					.
					<artpagenums>57 - 68</artpagenums>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
		</bibliodiv>
		<bibliodiv>
			<title>Learning Management Systems</title>
			<para></para>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel="About Moodle"
				xmlid="about moodle">
				Moodle.org
				<bibliomset relation="book">
					<title role="book">About Moodle</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation="book">
					Retrieved 3/20/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://docs.moodle.org/en/About_Moodle">
						http://docs.moodle.org/en/About_Moodle
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Munoz &amp; VanDuzer'
				xml:id='munoz &amp; vanduzer'>
				Munoz, K &amp; Van Duzer, J. (2005)
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<title role="book">
						Blackboard vs. Moodle: A Comparison of
						Satisfaction with Online Teaching and Learning
						Tools
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/19/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://www.humboldt.edu/~jdv1/moodle/all.htm">
						http://www.humboldt.edu/~jdv1/moodle/all.htm
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='SFSU ETAC' xml:id='sfsu'>
				San Francisco State University Educatonal Technology
				Advisory Committee (2006)
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<title role="book">
						ETAC Report: Viability of an Exclusive
						iLearn-based LMS Environment
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/19/2008 from
					<link xlink:href="http://snurl.com/23drh">
						http://snurl.com/23drh
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Moodlerooms' xml:id='moodlerooms'>
				Moodlerooms.com
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<title role="book">What is Moodlerooms</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/19/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://www.moodlerooms.com/what-is-moodlerooms.html">
						http://www.moodlerooms.com/what-is-moodlerooms.html
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
		</bibliodiv>
		<bibliodiv>
			<title>Generational Research</title>
			<para></para>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Bedroom Study'
				xml:id='Bedroom Study'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					The Bedroom Study
					<title role="book">
						The Bedroom Study Web site
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/19/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://www.thebedroomstudy.com/">
						http://www.thebedroomstudy.com/
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Reeves 2008' xml:id='reeves 2008'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<title role='book'>
						Do Generational Differences Matter in
						Instructional Design?
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://it.coe.uga.edu/itforum/Paper104/ReevesITForumJan08.pdf">
						http://it.coe.uga.edu/itforum/Paper104/ReevesITForumJan08.pdf
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
		</bibliodiv>
		<bibliodiv>
			<title>Research Methods</title>
			<para></para>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Randolph 2007'
				xml:id='Randolph 2007'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Randolph, J. J. (2007).
					<title role='book'>
						Multidisciplinary methods in educational
						technology research and development
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link xlink:href="http://snurl.com/237qt">
						http://snurl.com/237qt
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Watkins &amp; Schlosser (2003)'
				xml:id='Watkins &amp; Schlosser (2003)'>
				Watkins R. &amp; Schlosser, C. (2003).
				<bibliomset relation='article'>
					<title>
						Conceptualizing Educational Research in Distance
						Educations
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<title>
						The Quarterly Review of Distance Education
					</title>
					<volumenum>4</volumenum>
					<issuenum>(3)</issuenum>
					.
					<artpagenums>331 - 341</artpagenums>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
		</bibliodiv>
		<bibliodiv>
			<title>Multimedia, Web 2.0 and Related Technologies</title>
			<para></para>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='NMC &amp; Educause 2008'
				xml:id='NMC &amp; Educause 2008'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					New Media Consortium &amp; Educause Learning
					Initiative
					<title role='book'>
						The Horizon Report: 2008 Edition
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://www.nmc.org/pdf/2008-Horizon-Report.pdf">
						http://www.nmc.org/pdf/2008-Horizon-Report.pdf
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Mader 2006' xml:id='Mader 2006'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Mader, S (Editor) (2006).
					<title role='book'>Using Wiki in Education.</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link xlink:href="http://www.wikiineducation.com">
						http://www.wikiineducation.com
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Riismandel 2008'
				xml:id='Riismandel 2008'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Riismandel, P (2008)
					<title role='book'>
						How to manage video content in higher education.
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Streaming Media Magazine Industry Sourcebook 2008
					<pagenums>pp. 160 - 165</pagenums>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Silver 2008' xml:id='Silver 2008'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Silver, D. (2008)
					<title role='book'>
						History, Hype, and Hope: An Afterward
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					<title>First Monday</title>
					<volumenum>13</volumenum>
					<issuenum>(3)</issuenum>
					. Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link
						xlink:href="http://www.uic.edu/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/viewArticle/2143/1950">
						http://www.uic.edu/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/viewArticle/2143/1950
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Sun 2008' xml:id='Sun 2008'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Sun Services (2008)
					<title role='book'>
						Current Reality And Future Vistion: Open Virtual
						Worlds
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 3/15/2008 from
					<link xlink:href="http://snurl.com/23dn5">
						http://snurl.com/23dn5
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Stevenson 2007'
				xml:id='Stevenson 2007'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Stevenson (2007)
					<title role='book'>
						Tool, tutor, environment or resource: Exploring
						metaphors for digital technology and pedagogy
						using activity theory
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Computers &amp; Education.
					doi:10.1016/j.compedu.2007.09.001
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
		</bibliodiv>
		<bibliodiv>
			<title>Managing Technology And Change</title>
			<para></para>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Berkum 2005' xml:id='Berkum'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Berkum, S. (2005)
					<title role='book'>
						The art of project management
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Sebastopol, CA.
					<publishername>
						O'Reilly and Associates
					</publishername>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Lopp 2007' xml:id='Lopp 2007'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Lopp, M (2007)
					<title role='book'>
						Managing Humans: Biting and humorous takes of a
						software engineering manager.
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Berkeley, CA.
					<publishername>Apress.</publishername>
					Most (if not all) chapters can also be found online
					at:
					<link xlink:href="http://www.randsinrepose.com/">
						http://www.randsinrepose.com/
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='PMI 2004' xml:id='PMI 2004'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Project Management Institute (2004)
					<title role='book'>
						A Guide To The Project Management Body Of
						Knowledge (PMBOK Guide) Third Edition
					</title>
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Newton Square, PA.
					<publishername>
						Project Management Institute
					</publishername>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
			<bibliomixed xreflabel='Webster' xml:id='Webster'>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Webster, B. F.
					<title role='book'>
						The Art of 'Ware [version 2.0]
					</title>
					[Online]
				</bibliomset>
				<bibliomset relation='book'>
					Retrieved 4/15/2008 from:
					<link
						xlink:href="http://and-still-i-persist.com/?page_id=236">
						http://and-still-i-persist.com/?page_id=236
					</link>
				</bibliomset>
			</bibliomixed>
		</bibliodiv>
	</bibliography>
	<glossary id="glossary-of-terms">
		<title>Glossary</title>

		<para>
			The following list provides brief definitions of the terms
			used throughout this document
		</para>
		<glossentry xml:id="addie">
			<glossterm>ADDIE</glossterm>
			<glossdef>
				<para>
					Instructional design model consisting of five steps:
					Analysis, Design, Development, Impmentation and
					Evaluation.
				</para>
				<para>
					ADDIE is a Instructional design method, more
					particularly a Instructional systems design model.
					<emphasis>
						Source:
						<link
							xlink:href="http://edutechwiki.unige.ch/en/ADDIE">
							http://edutechwiki.unige.ch/en/ADDIE
						</link>
					</emphasis>
				</para>
			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
		<glossentry xml:id="xml">
			<glossterm>eXtensible Markup Language</glossterm>
			<acronym>XML</acronym>
			<glossdef>
				<para>
					A markup language developed by the World Wide Web
					Consortium as a complement or replacement for HTML.
					XML is widely used in the bussines world as an
					information exchange format. In the education work
					it has primarily been used for description of
					information in SCORM and IMS specifications.
				</para>
				<glossseealso otherterm="xml">XML</glossseealso>
			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
		<glossentry xml:id="ims">
			<glossterm>IMS</glossterm>
			<glossdef>
				<para>
					In 1997, IMS came into existence as a project within
					the National Learning Infrastructure Initiative of
					EDUCAUSE. While IMS got its start with a focus on
					higher education, the specifications published to
					date as well as ongoing projects address
					requirements in a wide range of learning contexts,
					including of course K-12 schools and corporate and
					government training.
				</para>
				<para>
					The scope for IMS specifications, broadly defined as
					"distributed learning," includes both online and
					off-line settings, taking place synchronously
					(real-time) or asynchronously. This means that the
					learning contexts benefitting from IMS
					specifications include Internet-specific
					environments (such as web-based course management
					systems) as well as learning situations that involve
					off-line electronic resources (such as a learner
					accessing learning resources on a CD-ROM). The
					learners may be in a traditional educational
					environment (school classroom, university), in a
					corporate or government training setting, or at
					home. For example, the IMS Learning Resources
					Meta-data Specification (
					<link
						xlink:href="http://www.imsglobal.org/metadata">
						http://www.imsglobal.org/metadata
					</link>
					), benefits the learner looking for information with
					a meta-data aware search tool both when the search
					is of web-based resources and when she or he is
					searching through a CD-ROM or DVD-ROM encyclopedia
					in their computer at home. Content developers who
					have implemented the IMS Learning Resources
					Meta-data Specification will have made it much
					easier for the people doing the search to find the
					resources they want in a much more efficient way,
					since meta-data allows users to be much more
					specific in the search terms they can specify.
				</para>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Source: IMS/GLC Website</emphasis>
				</para>
			</glossdef>
			<glosssee otherterm="ims-consortium" />
		</glossentry>
		<glossentry xml:id="ims-consortium">
			<glossterm>IMS Global Learning Consortium</glossterm>
			<glossdef>
				<para>
					IMS GLC is a global, nonprofit, member association
					that provides leadership in shaping and growing the
					learning and educational technology industries
					through collaborative support of standards,
					innovation, best practice and recognition of
					superior learning impact.
				</para>
				<para>
					IMS GLC represents more than 100 Contributing
					Members, Subscriber organizations and Common
					Cartridge Alliance participants. These participant
					organizations come from every sector of the global
					learning community. They include hardware and
					software vendors, educational institutions,
					publishers, government agencies, systems
					integrators, multimedia content providers, and other
					consortia. IMS provides a neutral forum in which
					members work together to advocate the use of
					technology to support and transform education and
					learning.
				</para>
			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
		<glossentry xml:id="JIT Training">
			<glossterm>Just In Time Training</glossterm>
			<acronym>JIT</acronym>
			<glossdef>
				<para>
					Training that is delivered as needed to the
					participant rather than scheduled in advance. Just
					In Time Training is primarily used in Performance
					Improvement to correct a problem that needs specific
					instruction for its resoilution
				</para>
				<para>
					Producing or conveying only the items that are
					needed by the next process when they are needed and
					in the quantity needed. Can even be used between
					facilities or companies.
					<emphasis>Source: Lean Advisors</emphasis>
				</para>
			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>

		<glossentry xml:id="lms">
			<glossterm>Learning Management System</glossterm>
			<acronym>LMS</acronym>
			<glossdef>
				<para>Some reasonable definition here.</para>
			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
		<glossentry xml:id="moodle">
			<glossterm>Moodle</glossterm>
			<glossdef>
				<para>
					Moodle is a course management system (CMS) - a free,
					Open Source software package designed using sound
					pedagogical principles, to help educators create
					effective online learning communities. You can
					download and use it on any computer you have handy
					(including webhosts), yet it can scale from a
					single-teacher site to a 50,000-student University.
					<emphasis>
						Source:
						<link
							xlink:href="http://mercury.unitedseminary.edu/mod/glossary/view.php?g=2">
							http://mercury.unitedseminary.edu/mod/glossary/view.php?g=2
						</link>
					</emphasis>
				</para>
				<glossseealso otherterm="lms">LMS</glossseealso>
			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
		<glossentry xml:id="OS">
			<glossterm>Open Source</glossterm>
			<glossdef>
				<para>Some reasonable definition here.</para>
			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
		<glossentry xml:id="OSD">
			<glossterm>Open Source Definition</glossterm>
			<glossdef>
				<para>Some reasonable definition here.</para>
			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
		<glossentry xml:id="scorm">
			<glossterm>Shareable Conntent Reference Model</glossterm>
			<acronym>SCORM</acronym>
			<glossdef>
				<para>Some reasonable definition here.</para>
			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
		<glossentry>
			<glossterm>XML</glossterm>
			<glosssee otherterm="xml" />
		</glossentry>
	</glossary>
	<appendix id="survey-instrument">
		<title>Survey Instrument</title>
		<para />
	</appendix>
</book>